Hello my friends and welcome back to
another Balders's Gate 3 character
building guide. Hope you're all doing
well. Today we're covering a build with
some of the best spell casting in the
game. A flavorful, powerful master of
magic with irresistible damage, massive
burst damage, excellent sustained damage
output, and the full utility of two
whole spell-casting classes wrapped into
a single character. We will command the
forces of death to lay waste to our
enemies by casting devastating spells
for free turn after turn after turn. And
with our excellent defenses, we will
laugh at our foes attempts to fight
back. All while commanding our own
personal army of deadly and disposable
minions in a build I'm calling the Lich
Queen of Char. Before I begin, I want to
take a quick moment to say thank you so
much to Original Nautical Fasmid for the
$5 donation, Tarantula for the $5, Paul
Kato for the $50, and Gonzalo Menafelita
and Terrantism for becoming channel
members. Thank you so much, my friends.
I really appreciate the support. It
really means a lot to me. All right,
let's ascend to godhood. We're using
Shadow Heart as the example character
here because of course this is primarily
a cleric build and she's the cleric of
the party, but also I think that this
build is incredibly flavorful for Shadow
Hart, especially the more power- hungry
and brutal versions of her story line.
If you're building this as a custom
character, what race you pick mostly
doesn't matter for this character. Um,
we get all of our weapon and armor
proficiencies anyways, and we don't need
particular skills because we're unlikely
to be doing most of the skill checks for
our party. So what rice you pick is up
to you for flavor. Some good options to
increase your power level of course
include halfling to reroll ones, always
extremely valuable for every character,
or wood elf or half wood elf for the
additional movement speed.
At first level, although this is
primarily going to be a cleric build,
we're going to start with a level of
wizard. Because of the way that wizard
spellcasting works in Boulders's Gate 3,
this is going to let us scribe almost
every wizard spell in the game to our
spell book. So, we can learn basically
every spell in the wizard spell list as
well as every spell on the cleric spell
list. Not only does this help us fulfill
our goal of being the most powerful
spellcaster out there, it also is going
to help us take maximum advantage of one
of the game's very most powerful items,
the staff of cherish necromancy, which
is going to be where the incredible
offensive power of this build comes
from. with the free casts of extremely
highlevel necromancy spells. Starting as
wizard is going to give us a bunch of
extra options to take advantage of that
as well as provide tons of utility
spells. We're starting with wizard at
first level because when we take cleric
at second level, that's going to mean
that any spells we cast using items and
scrolls are going to use our wisdom. And
we want our offensive spell casting to
be wisdom based because our cleric
spells are where a lot of our damage is
going to come from. So, we take wizard
at first level and then take cleric at
later levels. For our wizard cantrips,
therefore, we're looking for spells here
that don't require us to have high
intelligence in order to make offensive
attacks. So, nothing with a saving throw
or an attack role associated with it.
However, there's one exception to this
rule, which is that we can still take
booming blade. Booming blade doesn't
actually care about your casting stat
because it's made as part of a melee
attack. So, for this character in the
early game, we can use a dagger or
shortsord or other finesse weapon with
our high dexterity in order to make
booming blade attacks. This gives us a
pretty nice melee option in the early
game, and booming blade is entirely
free. So, having it on just about any
character is really powerful. Also, as a
death domain cleric, we're going to get
bonuses to our melee attacks in the late
game, and booming blade can stack with
those. So, that can still make this
character a reasonable melee threat. uh
it's not going to be your primary
strategy cuz you're mostly going to be a
full caster, but it's a nice option to
have. In addition to that, we're also
going to take minor illusion, grouping
enemies before combat starts and then
blowing them up is key to any
spell-casting character. And mage hand,
because the utility of mage hand is
unbeatable. Being able to drop potions
on the ground and have the mage hand
throw them at your allies in order to
heal them gives you basically an extra
character in some fights. For our spell
selection, we're doing something very
similar. Obviously, as a wizard, you're
going to be able to learn spells from
scrolls. So, your primary choice of
spells is going to be determined by what
scrolls you find throughout the game.
And as we level up, I'll talk about some
important spells to keep an eye out for.
But some really important spells are
ones that again don't have a saving
throw or attack role associated with
them and help your character out.
Enhanced leap and longstrider are
tremendous utility for the party and
excellent mandatory for pretty much any
party to have these two spells. They're
both rituals, so they don't cost a spell
slot to use outside of combat and are
basically free bonuses. Shield turns
this character's defenses excellent
because we will have medium armor and
shield proficiency from our death cleric
levels. So, combine that with the shield
spell and we're suddenly extremely hard
to kill. We can also add magic missile
to have guaranteed damage. This also
doesn't care about our intelligence and
it will always hit. So just the ability
to have add some guaranteed damage um
when we need it is very important to
finish off low health enemies. And uh
we'll take mage armor as well. There are
points in the game where you would
rather have a robe than the available
medium armor sets. And so mage armor can
allow you to do that. For our last spell
selection here, it's mostly going to be
dependent on what scrolls you find and
what spells you like. Things like find
familiar or fogcloud make very good
utility spells as well. Finally, for our
ability score selection, we're going to
take a very unusual attribute split for
a wizard because we're going to start
with eight intelligence. Um, this means
we're only going to be able to cast one
spell on the nautilloid. So, if you're
building this character from level one
and not respspecking shadow heart into
it when you get to withers, um, you're
going to want to use a light crossbow
combined with your 16 dexterity in order
to fight on the nauttoloid. And the
spell you'll use is probably magic
missile when you only have access to one
spell. Later on, we'll use the headband
of intellect to set our intelligence to
17. And that will let us prepare and
cast four wizard spells, which is plenty
because wizard spell casting is going to
be primarily for utility. So, we can
swap those around outside of combat to
make sure that we're getting all of our
spell casting available. Then, we're
going to take 17 wisdom um to maximize
our cleric spell casting. And with the
last two remaining points, you can
either put these in intelligence because
the saving throw is relevant or put them
in strength for extra carry weight.
Either of those is fine. Um, since
wizards get proficiency in intelligence
saving throws naturally, I like just
putting these last two points in
strength for carry weight. This
character is going to be in medium armor
and carrying a lot of stuff. So, having
the 10 points of strength can be nice
utility. We're taking an odd number in
wisdom here because we're either going
to use Ethel's hair or Khaled's gift.
the amulet in order to get one extra
point of wisdom so that we only need one
feat to still hit 20. Um, if you really
hate using any stat items, you can still
build this character without the
headband of intellect or Khaled's gift
or Ethel's hair. It just requires
putting up to 14 points in intelligence.
So, you're going to sacrifice a little
dexterity and then you'll need
initiative gear to make up for not
having alert. So, if you really hate um
using attribute items, you can still do
that for this character. All right,
that's all the relevant decisions we
have to make at level one because our
skills mostly don't matter for this
character. So, just take whatever you
want for flavor. And then let's move on
to level two. At character level two,
we're immediately leaving wizard and
we're going to take a level of cleric.
For our cleric subclass, we're going to
take death domain cleric, which is going
to make enemies unable to resist our
necrotic damage at later levels. So,
even though a lot of enemies in this
game are resistant to necrotic damage,
we're still going to be able to just
obliterate enemies with our necromancy
spells. Uh, we also get the ability to
double up on our necromancy cantrips,
which makes us incredibly powerful in
the early game. Between magic missile
and um, and our wizard cantrips giving
us extra utility and our cleric cantrips
doubling up, this character is one of
the best early game spellcasters even
before we get any of our other abilities
online. For our cantrip selection here,
we are going to first take our death
domain unique cantrip, which gives us
the option to take bursting senue, bone
chill, or toll the dead. If you're on
console, you need to go forward until
you get to this screen and then go
backwards before picking your cleric
cantrips. Um, because otherwise it will
not let you pick uh toll the dead as one
of your cleric cantrips because it
defaults to toll the dead as one of your
as your death domain cantrip. So, we're
going to take bone chill for our death
domain cantrips. And then for our cleric
cantrips, we're going to take toll the
dead. Guidance, of course, because it's
just the best spell in the game. Um, and
in addition to that, we're going to take
bursting senue. Not because it's
particularly good, but because it's
incredibly flavorful for this character
and so much fun to use. So, I still just
like taking it on death domain clerics.
Told the dead and bone chill are going
to be our main offensive options. For
our prepared spells at this level, you
are looking for command, of course. Uh,
this powerful control spell is going to
be the best thing to cast that's not
concentration basically throughout the
entire game. And a lot of your spell
slots are going to be used for command
when they're not used for directly
killing enemies. Sanctuary, which is an
amazing panic button and also makes this
character excellent at concentrating on
haste if that's something that you want
to do, which you get by virtue of act of
having the wizard level. And then we're
going to add in healing ward. Um, of
course, a great defensive ability uh to
get allies up who have been knocked down
and inflict wounds. Inflict wounds works
really well as a death domain cleric
because we're going to do tons of melee
burst damage and later on we're going to
be able to cast this spell for free
without spending a spell slot. So, it's
a tremendous amount of additional
damage.
At character level three, we're taking
our second level of cleric, which as a
death cleric gets us channel divinity,
touch of death. This is a super powerful
ability for this character because once
per short rest, it allows us to add five
plus double our cleric level in necrotic
damage to a melee attack. This doesn't
have to be a melee weapon attack,
although because we have booming blade
and 16 dexterity. We can use a dagger or
shortsord to apply channel divindy and
that's pretty powerful with a booming
blade attack. But it also allows us to
add extra burst damage to any other
melee attack such as inflict wounds. So
you can add nine extra damage to the
damage of an inflict wounds. Adding nine
damage to an attack is the same average
damage as a smite from a paladin. So
channel divinity touch of death makes
this character again have tremendous
burst damage with inflict wounds. With
melee attacks using booming blade, you
can then walk away from the enemy and
force them to take the extra booming
blade damage when they follow you. And
of course, great ranged damage as well
because doubling up on bone chill or
toll the dead allows us to hit multiple
enemies with powerful ranged cantrip
attacks which at this level do excellent
damage. We're also now level three which
means we get second level wizard spell
casting. So we can get powerful
offensive spells that don't rely on
having high intelligence like cloud of
daggers in order to supplement the
additional burst damage that we get. So
you can concentrate on cloud of daggers
and then use a burst effect like inflict
wounds plus touch of death uh which
doesn't require your concentration to
blow up any enemies that survive that.
So even from the beginning the array of
spell-casting options that we have with
this character are immense.
At character level three we are taking
our third level of cleric which gets us
access to second level cleric spells
including our domain spells from death
domain cleric. Blindness is actually a
really nice spell to have as as a domain
spell because it's a 10 turn long
non-conentration debuff. Enemies do get
a save to break out of it each of their
turns, but this is still a very powerful
option for longer fights. Normally, you
don't want to use a spell prepared slot
on blindness, but when you have it as a
domain spell, you always have access to
this. So, it makes a really nice option.
Ray of Infeblement you're almost
certainly not actually using, but
blindness is a pretty nice domain spell
for death domain clerics to have. For
our prepared spells at this level, we're
going to add a couple more spells into
our potential spell list. We're going to
add in spiritual weapon, which is only a
bonus action to cast and can distract
enemies. This is the first of the many
creatures that we're going to add to our
gigantic army. Um, and then we're going
to add hold person. One spell that
you'll note is missing from this spell
list is bless. You can still use bless
of course if that's what you want to
concentrate on. Uh and it's really nice
for this character because we do make
attack rolls, but because we have so
many other powerful spell options, um
we're going to mostly use the buff on
heal items to apply bless in the early
game with this character rather than
casting it ourselves. Though it is still
a really nice option as well. Hold
person is extremely synergistic for
death domain cleric because critical
hits work on inflict wounds since it's
an attack role. So if you hold person
somebody and then use inflict wounds on
them, you do double damage with that
inflict wounds, you can then add
channelneled divinity to it. So this is
another way to burst down enemies with
tremendous amounts of direct damage.
At level five, we're taking our fourth
level of cleric. And of course, because
we are now a level five spellcaster with
a level of wizard, we also get access to
thirdle wizard spells. Now, notably,
there's one missing from this list cuz
there's no scroll of counter spell, but
this still gets us a really nice
selection of utility spells from wizard
at level three that we can scribe from
scrolls. Haste is a really important
one, and this character is really good
at concentrating on haste. So keep an
eye out for a scroll of haste cuz you
can cast haste on an ally and then
sanctuary yourself and then enemies will
not be able to interrupt your
concentration on haste. So for fights
where you maybe have fewer spell slots
or your spell casting is not as powerful
and you want to focus on buffing an
ally, that's a very strong option as
well. For a cantrip selection at this
level, we're going to go ahead and pick
up resistance. Resistance is a nice one
to have for certain story events that
require you to make saving throws. And
so just having access to this is really
good somewhere in your party. And then
for our feet, of course, this is an
honor mode character, so we're going to
take alert because going first means
that enemies don't often get to go
second, especially with a character with
so much lockdown and burst damage as
this character has. I also say that
alert is for honor mode characters, but
it's for every difficulty, even if
you're playing on lower difficulties.
Sometimes I get the question, what
should I take on lower difficulties? And
the answer is still alert because going
first is incredibly powerful in Dungeons
and Dragons and in Boulders Gate 3 in
particular where burst damage is so
excellent as it is on this character.
At character level six, we're taking our
fifth level of cleric, which of course
gets us third level cleric spells. This
includes as a domain spell animate dead.
Animate dead is a pretty powerful option
to give us an army of creatures to
follow us. Uh, at this level, spending a
third level spell slot on animate dead
won't always be the most efficient. But
there are some fights where an army of
zombies can just solve that fight
immediately. If you're fighting against
a lot of weak enemies, the zombies can
propagate themselves and you can end up
with a huge number of zombies on your
side. And the skeleton archers are
always a pretty powerful option as well.
They just add a little bit of consistent
damage to your party throughout the
entire day. for prepared spells at this
level as a cleric. We're going to add
two more spells to our spell list and
those of course are spirit guardians and
glyph of warding. Spirit guardians works
with death cleric's ability to ignore
enemy necrotic resistance. So you can do
necrotic damage in addition to the
normal radiant damage that this can do.
And in combination with the fact that we
have medium armor, shield proficiency,
and the shield spell, enemies are not
going to be able to hurt this character.
So you can play in melee range with
spirit guardians running very safely and
use your powerful death cleric melee
burst damage to kill enemies while also
damaging other enemies at the same time.
Of course, you can do the normal thing
that clerics do and use radiant damage
with the spirit guardians as well to
debuff enemies with radiating orb and
reverberation stacks and that's an
extremely powerful option as well. But
death cleric gives you a whole extra
layer of strategy with spirit guardians
cuz there's some enemies you don't want
to do radiant damage to and in that case
you can do necrotic damage. Glyph of
warding is just a spammable powerful
non-conentration damage option. Um you
can use it to create ice surfaces to
knock enemies over, put enemies to
sleep. Just a very powerful and flexible
spell. So of course we're going to take
it. At character level seven, we're
again continuing to level up in cleric.
And now we get inescapable destruction
as a death cleric, which means that our
spells ignore resistance to necrotic
damage. Resistance to necrotic damage is
extraordinarily prevalent in Falers Gate
3. There's a lot of undead that have
resistance to necrotic damage and just a
lot of enemies in general that have
necrotic resistance. So, inescapable
destruction makes a damage type that is
somewhat awkward to use in this game
incredibly powerful for death clerics
because nothing resists it. There are a
couple enemies that are immune, but this
means that it it takes a damage type
that is one of the narrowest in terms of
what you can effectively use it against
and turns it into one of the broadest.
So now these powerful necrotic spells
work on everything. We also of course
get uh fourth level wizard spells. There
aren't that many utility spells that you
need from wizard at fourth level. So,
um, while there are some scrolls that
are kind of interesting, like greater
invisibility that you can scribe and use
to give your party members stealth and
things like that, there's nothing in
particular that you desperately need to
keep an eye out for from wizard uh from
fourth level wizard spells. But, of
course, you're going to collect all of
them that you can get scrolls from for
anyways, so might as well describe
everything.
At character level eight, we get our
fourth level cleric spells. And one of
the nice things about this character is
we get a new spell level. Every level,
whether wizard spells or cleric spells,
we're always, every time we level up,
gaining access to a new tier of spells.
So, every single level is exciting when
you're playing through the game with
this character. Um, this gives us also
two more domain spells, and this
includes blight. Now, blight is normally
a fairly weak spell. Uh, but because
this is necrotic resistant, uh, because
we're a death domain cleric, we ignore
necrotic resistance. Blight actually has
some pretty useful uses for this
character. Plants take maximum damage
from blight, meaning it always does 64
damage to them, but the only plants in
the game at the point where you get this
spell uh, have resistance to necrotic
damage. So most characters cannot
possibly use blight effectively. Death
domain clerics on the other hand can use
blight to kill the uh enemies that are
plants and have necrotic resistance in
act two very effectively. This also is a
good spell to spam with the spe with the
staff of cherish necromancy which of
course is one of the game's most
powerful items and what this build is
centered around maximizing. And so
blight is a really good spell to have as
a domain spell. We also get death ward,
which you should rarely cast unless
you're abusing a bug with it. Um, for
our prepared spells at this level, we're
going to add in a couple more spell
options. And in this case, we're going
to add in banishment because this
targets enemy charisma saving throws.
It's really useful against certain
bosses. So, you can swap this out when
you're not using it specifically. And
we'll also add in freedom of movement.
This is a good panic button cuz it can
break an ally out of a stun. Um, so if
you accidentally stop concentrating on
haste and stun an ally or if they get
stunned by an enemy, freedom of movement
can snap them out of it. So I just like
to have this spell prepared. We can
also, of course, pick up any spells that
we feel like we are really missing from
earlier levels, but this will be a good
default spell list, especially when you
combine it with the utility spills that
you get from wizard.
character level nine, we're taking our
eighth level of cleric, and that gets us
divine strike necrotic. Now, divine
strike uh necrotic means that we add an
extra d8 necrotic damage to all of our
weapon attacks, which will actually be
relevant for this character if we're
attacking with booming blade attacks um
using a finesse weapon. That again is
not going to be a primary strategy, but
if you are out of anything else to do,
then that still is pretty decent damage.
By this point, we're level nine. So,
booming blade does an initial d8 of
thunder damage and then two d8 if
enemies move and you add a d8 from this
and then you attack with your weapon.
So, if you're completely out of other
resources, that's actually a totally
reasonable thing to do if you find
yourself in a bind and just need some
extra damage. Um, mostly you probably
won't be using this ability because it
requires a weapon attack unlike your
other death cleric melee ability. Um,
but divine strike necrotic does make you
an okay melee attacker when the
situation calls for it. In addition to
that, of course, we get a feat. And the
feat that we're going to take is an
ability improvement to boost our wisdom,
making our spell save DCs and damage and
everything significantly higher. We also
get fifth level wizard spells. And
there's a few spells that are very
important to learn here, but the most
notable one is going to be conjure
elemental. Conjure elemental is the best
summon in the game. uh we can use it
either with fifth level spell slots or
with sixth level spell slots and get
tremendous value from it. And since this
character is so good at summoning an
army because we're going to be able to
have a fully powered up animate dead, a
fully powered up create undead, a planer
ally if we refresh our level six spell
slot, and a murmuron if we refresh our
level six spell slot. You can be walking
around with a whole personal army just
from this character alone.
Character level 10, we get fifth level
cleric spells. And that includes because
we are a death domain cleric, contagion,
and cloudkill. Contagion is also a nice
spell to have as a domain spell,
especially because again, it's a
necromancy spell, so we can cast it for
free using the staff of terish
necromancy. That remains a very powerful
option. And although contagion is a
spell that's mostly used outside of
combat, um you can use contagion to get
tremendous value if you cast it before
combat begins. If enemies fail the
saving throws, then the contagion
debuffs will just win any fight that
you're in. Enemies getting stunned every
time they take damage or having
vulnerability to all damage types from
contagion is absolutely brutal. For a
bigger a longer breakdown on this spell
effect, check out my recent spell tier
list where I talk about it a lot. And
while you again don't usually want to
waste a spell prepared slot on it or
spell slots on it, when you get it for
free and don't have to prepare it, this
spell is really nice to have. Cloud kill
is also a pretty solid one. Uh there are
some fights where enemies are not immune
to poison and you can cast cloud kill on
top of them. We're a cleric, so we could
have heroes feast up if we have enough
sources of free spell casting. And then
we're immune to the damage you can fight
inside your own cloud kills. So very
powerful set of domain spells. This is
the kind of domain spell I like, by the
way. A situational effect that's very
powerful that you wouldn't usually want
to prepare, but is really nice for some
encounters. So having it as a domain
spell lets you use it more freely. For
our prepared spells at this level, we're
mostly going back to pick up spells from
earlier spell levels that we might need
because our uh spell options as a fifth
level cleric are mostly not great. So,
you can go back and grab other potential
options. Things like mass healing word
to apply the buff on heal items if
you're using those. Um things like
enhance ability, which can be useful for
some late game skill checks. even things
like bless or create water which are
utilities or of course aid which you can
spend a spell slot on to boost your
whole party's uh HP and aid is really
nice given that we have so many summons
though that again gets a little spell
slot hungry
character level 11 we get our sixth
level spell slot which means that we can
upcast lower level spells to level six
including necromancy spells that we're
almost certainly able to cast for free
by this point in the game cuz we should
have gotten the staff of cherished
necromancy. So that can let you use a
level six animate dead for free. It can
let you cast blight at level six for
free, cast inflict wounds at level six
for free. Um so that's an extremely
powerful option to have. It also of
course gets us access to sixth level
wizard spells. And the most important
utility spell to have from wizard at
sixth level is globe of invulnerability
which you can get a scroll for and learn
it. And then that just wins certain
encounters by making you completely
immune to damage. So this character's
offensive power is immense, as is their
defensive power. We also get a cantrip
selection here. Unfortunately, clerics
don't get access to true strike, so we
can't take that to annoy people in the
comments. Uh so let's just take Thelma
because it's kind of funny to just yell
at people in the late game.
And finally, at cleric level 11,
character level 12, we get our sixth
level cleric spells. And there's several
here that are really nice for us, even
nicer than they usually are for clerics.
So, of course, we are going to be a
somewhat summon focused build. So,
planer ally is the best cleric summon
spell with some really powerful summons
associated with it. But the spell that
usually takes a backseat to planer ally
is create undead. The mummy is
significantly worse than the planer ally
summons. It's also worse than the
Merdons, which we can also summon, but
it's a necromancy spell because we're
going to be able to cast these for free
without spending spell slots. We can
summon this sixth level summon for free
over and over again. And if it dies,
which it sometimes will because you
they're hard to heal and they're not
that tough, uh you can just reummon it.
So, you get an endless legion of
disposable and extraordinarily powerful
minions from the existence of great
undead at this level. We also get access
to heroes feast, another level six spell
that you can use. You will not, even
with all the free spell casting in the
game, be able to cast every sixth level
spell that you want, but you can get
pretty close. So you can have heroes
feast running, you can have Mermadon
running, you can have a planer ally
running with the three free spell casts,
and then you can use your staff of
cherish necromancy casts to also cast a
level six animate dead and a level six
create undead. Um, and then still have a
sixle spell slot, assuming that you use
Marahesh gear, the spellcrux amulet, and
the pre-cast a lithid power for the
other three. you can still have a sixle
spell slot to spam during the day with
the stash staff of cherish necromancy.
So that's going to be your spell setup
in the endame if you want to absolutely
maximize the number of uh minions and
the amount of power that you have
available. All right, my friends, that
is the lich queen of char. An
extraordinarily powerful character with
amazing burst damage, but of course we
can make the character better with uh
items. So, let's talk about those. For
items for this character, we are
interested, of course, in enhancing our
spell casting and increasing our
defenses. So, those are the two main
things that we're looking for in items.
For our weapon, there's only one choice
in the endame, and that is the staff of
cherish necromancy. This build is built
in part to maximize the power of this
incredibly powerful item. So, that's the
weapon that we're going to use. Up until
that point, you can use any staff that
gives you an increase to your spell save
DC uh because that's the only stat that
you care about from your weapon. The
staff of Cheriff necromancy, of course,
gives you life essence harvest. When you
kill a creature with a spell, you get
life essence, which you can use to cast
a necromancy spell for free. That's
what's going to let us just use
incredibly highlevel and extraordinarily
powerful spells over and over and over
again. Not only can we use this to do
things like upcast inflict wounds at
level six, we can use it to upcast
blight using a level six spell. Um we
can also use it to do things like upcast
animate dead to summon three flying
ghouls. Uh we can use it to upcast
create undead to summon a mummy. These
are all necromancy spells so we can cast
them for free when we have life essence.
In addition to that, we're going to want
a shield. Uh and there's really two
choices for shield. You can use the
sentinel shield for plus three tier
initiative. This character probably
wants to get one or two points of
initiative boost somewhere in the build
because we have plus eight which is very
good of course but plus 10 means that
you are guaranteed to go before all but
the very fastest enemies in the game and
you're competitive with them. So adding
in the sentinel shield for plus 11
initiative is really nice. The
alternative is to use ketherix shield
which increases your spell save DCs and
so that will allow you to uh land your
spells more easily. In the early game,
you're probably going to want to use the
buff on heal item set. So that consists
of the hell riders pride which gives
blade ward to allies that you heal and
the whispering promise which blesses
allies that you heal. You can use this
also by throwing a potion at them. It
doesn't have to be a healing spell but
we have healing word so we can apply
healing with a bonus action. makes us a
very good user for this item set. Um,
and you can supplement that with the
boots of a comfort for three temp HP and
the ring of salving for additional
healing, though that's less important
since this isn't really a main healer.
If you really like this item set and
want to keep using it into the late
game, you'll swap out the Hell Rider's
Pride for the Reviving Hands, which is
the same effect, but works on yourself
and also gives you revivify once uh that
you can cast once per long rest. We also
have a couple items that we need in
order to make the build function. We're
looking for the warped headband of
intellect. So, you're going to want to
get this relatively early because we
need to be able to prepare wizard
spells. The number of spells that you
can prepare from a class is equal to
your class level, which in this case is
one plus your uh casting bonus for that
class, which for us with eight
intelligence means we could only prepare
one wizard spell. Adding the headband of
intellect lets us prepare four, which
gives us a lot more optionality with our
wizard spell casting. So, this character
can use this. Luckily, this item is not
particularly in demand. Uh, so it
shouldn't be contested by other builds
in your party. In addition to that,
we're either going to want to use
Ethel's hair to boost our wisdom up to
20 or use Khaled's gift in order to
boost our wisdom up to 20. Of course, we
want 20 wisdom on this character. So
having plus one to our wisdom from one
of those two sources is very important.
Um if you're using Ethel's hair, you can
use as your other amulet the amulet of
the devout which gives you additional
spell save DC uh and extra channel
divinity which is very useful for for uh
these characters as well. Um cuz of
course that lets us use our touch of
death more often. Uh and or the amulet
of greater health which will let us set
our constitution to the maximum. Um, and
that will to set our constitution to 23.
Then we can take these points out of
constitution and put them in
intelligence. And that can let us use a
different helmet. So if you want to use
the amulet of greater health, put these
points from constitution into
intelligence, then you don't need the
warped headband of intellect anymore and
can swap that out for something like the
hood of the weave, which makes you even
more powerful. And that's what this
character is set up as for the endgame
scenario. So, in the early game, warped
headband. Later on, maybe you swap to
the amulet of greater health and use the
hood of the weave. There's also a couple
uh we for our armor. Excuse me, I just
got got myself turned around there. Um
for our armor, there are two options for
whether we want more offensive or more
defensive armor. We have medium armor
proficiency, so we can use something
like the armor of agility. That'll get
us pretty solid armor class with uh 22
base AC before we have any other items
or effects. and it gives you plus two to
your saving throws, which can help keep
this character alive. Another defensive
option with slightly lower AC, but with
plus two initiative is the flame and
ambled armor. This gives us resistance
to fire damage, resistance to cold
damage when we cast the fire shield
spell. So for any fight where we want
resistance to cold damage, we have it.
Plus two our saving throws, and plus two
to our initiative as well. So depending
on whether we want more initiative or
more AC, the defensive options are going
to be those two suits of armor.
Alternatively, we can use mage armor,
which we know as a wizard, and the robe
of the weave or another robe in order to
increase our spell save DCs even
further. So, there's a couple different
setups, and it'll depend exactly on what
other items your party members need,
which of these setups you're going to go
with. For our boots, we're focused on
defensive options. So, an armor like the
evasive shoes is really nice just to
give us extra armor class. Or the boots
of striding because that will prevent us
from being knocked prone while
concentrating, which we're going to be
doing in a lot of fights, especially if
you're making aggressive use of spirit
guardians to run up to enemies. Also
important for this character, and I
talked about this during spell
selection, the items that let you use
spell slots for free or restore them,
the spellcrux amulet and marahesh gear
are very important for this character.
And something important about these
items is that you can use them and then
pass them to another party member. And
so each party member can use them. So
even if you have another character
that's using Mara, you can still have
this character cast heroes feast or
whatever for free and then pass off
Maraheshare. So these items are
incredibly valuable since our sixth
level spell slots let us do basically
every good sixth level spell in the
game. So we definitely want to have
those available. Uh, also of course we
can use anything that increases our
spell save DC like the ring of fay wild
sparks in addition to our other setups
here. Um, this doesn't have it listed
but in it increases your spell save DCs
by one so is really good for any
spell-casting character. Finally, of
course, just like any other cleric,
another option is to use the radiating
orb item set. We of course have spirit
guardians and plenty of sources of
radiant damage. So, we can use the
luminous armor, callus glow ring, and
coruscation ring in order to apply
radiating orbs to enemies while we run
at them with spirit guardians and hit
them with our spells. And we can also
stack uh reverberation stacks of the
gloves of belligerent skies and boots of
stormy clamor. So, that's another
different way that we could build the
character if we want to focus more on
debuffing. You still get all of the
spell casting power, but are a more
traditional cleric using the radiating
orb item set if you want to go that
route. Finally, it's worth mentioning a
couple spells that are that we can
scribe from scrolls that are normally
pretty terrible, but that this character
can make amazing use of. Um, and these
are circle of death and dethrone. Circle
of death is a gigantic AoE damage spell,
but it only does the same amount of
damage as fireball, so most characters
are never going to want to spend a sixth
level spell slot on it. But because it's
a nec necromancy spell, this character
with the staff can cast it for free. And
there are some fights where just a huge
AoE is what you need because it ignores
resistance as well. It's usable in a lot
more circumstances for this character.
And although it will key off of our
intelligence uh because it's a wizard
spell in the end game, that won't matter
as much um because we're going to have
17 intelligence from the warped headband
and a bunch of spell DC gear. So, our
save DCs, even on our wizard spells,
won't be awful. And then we'll also be
giving enemies disadvantage on those
saves because of the staff of cherish
necromancy, giving them disadvantage
against on saves against any of our
necromancy spells. So, even aggressive
uh wizard spells can be used in the
endame. Spells like circle of death in
order to do a bunch of AoE damage. It's
not going to be every turn or anything,
but this is a good option to have. The
other one is dethrone. And this allows
us to take advantage of a bug in the
game um that normally makes it makes
this spell very bad. So this is one of
the secret spells only you can only get
it if you're a wizard and you scribe it
from a scroll cuz you find a scroll of
this spell and it does a bunch of direct
damage at a very long range. It's a 100
ft range. Um, and normally, again, this
is a very weak spell, but this character
cast it for free cuz it's a necromancy
spell and ignores resistance to the
damage. And the main problem with this
spell is that it has a fixed save DC of
18. It's bugged. So, for most wizards,
it's going to be a significant downgrade
on the spell save compared to just
casting any of their other spells. But
this character actually that's an
upgrade for because our wizard spells
are using our quite low intelligence. So
the fixed DC of 18, we don't care about
it. Actually helps us uh at some points
in the game and they'll have
disadvantage on the save cuz it's a
necromancy spell. We'll cast it for
free. So this character makes really
good use of dethrone unlike any other
character in the game who doesn't want
to use it cuz it costs them something
very expensive for not much return. So,
very very powerful option here with your
fifth level spell slots. Very powerful
option with uh Circle of Death with your
sixth level spell slots. And these
spells are great for this character even
though they're garbage for everyone
else. All right, my friends. I hope that
you've enjoyed this look at the Lich
Queen of Char. And I hope you enjoy
running around with a gigantic army and
blowing up anyone who dares to look at
you funny with your incredible mastery
of magic. As always, of course, if
you've enjoyed the video, feel free to
leave a comment and hit like. Helps me
out with the algorithm, so I appreciate
you taking the time to do that. And of
course, you can subscribe to my channel
for more Balders's Gate 3 build guides
and other strategy game analysis.
Cheers, my friends. I'll catch you next